Guide to the Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb Collection on the Occupy Wall Street Library TAM.775
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb Collection on the Occupy Wall Street Library
1998-2014
2011-2012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taylor, Jaime
Loeb, Zachary
TAM.775
4.8 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, a flat box, an oversized flat box, a cassette box, 3 folders in a shared flat box, 12 folders in a shared oversized flat box, and 3 flat file folders.
Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb are librarians who were active in the Occupy Wall Street Library. The Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb Collection on the Occupy Wall Street Library (dated 1998-2014) consists of materials created and collected by Taylor and Loeb. The collection documents the Occupy Wall Street (OWS) encampment at Zuccotti Park in New York City; the creation, activities, and belongings of the OWS Library; the political activities of OWS and affiliated protests; and the library's eviction from the park by the New York Police Department (NYPD). Materials in this collection include ephemera, correspondence, administrative files, protest fliers, zines, and realia – some of which are directly related to the library's eviction by the NYPD in November 2011. The collection also includes a small amount of materials on librarianship, including an article and conference programs.
Biographical Note
Jaime Taylor is a librarian who was active in the Occupy Wall Street Library. Taylor has worked as a librarian in both the public and private spheres. Her professional interests include the racialized and gendered nature of librarianship; the rethinking of librarian education; flattening institutional structures beyond the norm; and library technology and management's intersections with neoliberal capitalism.
Biographical Note
Zachary Loeb is a librarian who was active in the Occupy Wall Street Library. Prior to earning his PhD from the University of Pennsylvania, Loeb earned an MA from the Department of Media, Culture, and Communication at New York University; and an MSIS from the Information School at the University of Texas at Austin. He has worked for several libraries including the Center for Jewish History; the New York Public Library; and the Kislak Center for Special Collections, Rare Books, and Manuscripts.
Historical Note
The Occupy Wall Street (OWS) Library, also known as the People's Library, was founded in September 2011 by Occupy Wall Street protesters in Lower Manhattan's Zuccotti Park and was led by librarian Betsy Fagin. Over time, the People's Library received books and resource donations from readers, private citizens, authors, and corporations. Musician Patti Smith also contributed a tent to the library, which was named Fort Patti in her honor, and was used as the library's primary structure until it was destroyed in November 2011.
On November 15, 2011, officers from the New York Police Department (NYPD) and employees from the New York City Department of Sanitation (DSNY) forcibly evicted everyone in Zuccotti Park. Following a decision ordered by New York City officials and the Park's owners (Brookfield Office Properties), NYPD and DSNY employees loaded the library's approximately 5,500+ book collection into garbage trucks and moved them to a sanitation site. Although New York City mayor, Michael Bloomberg, stated the library's collection was safely stored at the sanitation site and could be retrieved at a later date, library representatives later learned most of the library's collection and equipment had been destroyed, damaged, or lost.
In May 2012, the OWS Library sued Mayor Michael Bloomberg, Police Commissioner Raymond Kelly, and Sanitation Commissioner John Doherty in federal court. In April 2013, the city was ordered to pay $366,700 to the People's Library for the raid.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Administrative, Legal, and Conference Materials
Series II: Ephemera, Realia, and Protest Materials
Series III: Publications
Within each series, materials are listed in alphabetical order by format and then by title.
Scope and Contents
The Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb Collection on the Occupy Wall Street Library (dated 1998-2014) consists of materials created and collected by librarians Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb. The collection documents the Occupy Wall Street (OWS) encampment at Zuccotti Park in New York City; the creation, activities, and belongings of the OWS Library, also referred to as The People's Library; political activities of OWS and affiliated protests; and the library's eviction from the park by the New York Police Department (NYPD) on November 15, 2011, which lay the groundwork for the subsequent lawsuit against the city of New York.
Materials in this collection include administrative files, correspondence, and legal resources; ephemera and posters; protest materials; examples of library holdings and zines published by local artists; publications, both from within the OWS movement and outside; and realia including a broken laptop and cashbox, which are directly related to the library's eviction by the NYPD in November 2011. The collection also includes a small amount of materials on librarianship, including an article by Taylor and Loeb; and conference programs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb in November 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2021.024.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Appraisal
On October 30, 2023, Curator for Tamiment Collections Shannon O'Neill and Head of Archival Collections Management Weatherly Stephan discussed the nature of the damaged electronics within this collection. Electronics in the collection include a Kindle, a laptop, and a radio receiver. This technology was used to serve the Occupy Wall Street Library, also known as the People's Library. All of the electronics and hardware presently in the collection sustained damage during the NYPD's raid and eviction of the People's Library on November 15th, 2011. As such, they are inoperable. Going forward, these items serve as artifactual evidence of the destruction of the Library. We will retain them for this purpose; however, the technology is not meant to be utilized and no data that may possibly exist on the technology is retrievable.
In March 2025, attempts were made to image two optical discs using FTK Imager, however, these attempts were unsuccessful and these discs were removed from the collection. One optical disc containing a video was imaged using IsoBuster, however due to the copyright nature of the video's content, this disc was removed from the collection. Copies of The Nation, International Socialist Review, Labor Notes, Time Magazine, Village Voice, am New York, The Catholic Worker, The Indypendent and Occupy! Gazette -- all of which are dated between 2011 and 2012 -- were removed from the collection due to online accessibility from the publisher's individual websites.
Occupy movement -- New York (State) -- New York.; Protest movements -- United States.; Librarians -- Political activity -- United States.; Libraries -- New York (N.Y.); Social movements.; Capitalism.; Income distribution; New York (N.Y.).; Legal aid -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Artifacts.; Publications (documents); May Day (Labor holiday).; Zines; Posters.; Occupy Wall Street (Movement)
- Series I: Administrative, Legal, and Conference Materials, 2007-2014; 2011-2012; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1.5 manuscript boxes, 2 folders in a shared oversized flat box, and a flat file folder
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series consist of administrative files including library staff business cards and name tags; lists of International Standard Book Numbers (ISBNs) for library holdings; Occupy Wall Street (OWS) Action Planning meeting minutes and notes; OWS project lists and proposals; and official documents related to OWS's general assembly. Legal resources in this series include "Know Your Rights" handouts; lists of accessible legal aid organizations; jail support and bail information; and blank worksheets for reporting police brutalities. The series also contains Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb's conference materials where they discussed the role of the People's Library, the materials the Library collected, and their experiences working at the Library. A small amount of correspondence and religious sermons can also be found in this series.
  - Administrative Files -- Business Cards of Library Staff Members, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Files -- The Community Agreement of Occupy Wall Street (Draft), 2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Files --The Declaration of the Occupation of New York City by the NYC General Assembly, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Files -- Handwritten Notes, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 4, Flat-file-folder 5)
  - Administrative Files -- International Standard Book Numbers (ISBNs), 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Files -- Lawsuit and Settlement, 2011, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Files -- Library Staff Name Tags, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Files -- Occupy Wall Street Accounting, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Files -- Occupy Wall Street Action Planning Meeting, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Files -- Occupy Wall Street Library Notebook with Notes, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Files -- Occupy Wall Street Project List: A Guide to Ongoing Occupy Actions and Activities Around NYC, 2012 (Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 35)
  - Administrative Files -- Occupy Wall Street Structure Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Files -- Proposal to Restructure General Assembly, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Files -- What is Accountability in Occupy Wall Street?, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Files -- Working Group and Caucus Spokes Council Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Legal Resources -- Arrest Intake Form (National Lawyers Guild New York Chapter), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Legal Resources -- Dealing with Police and Police Misconduct Report, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Legal Resources -- The Dissident's Survival Guide, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Legal Resources -- How to Document Your Injuries for Lawsuits and the Media, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Legal Resources -- "Know Your Rights!" Handouts, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Legal Resources -- Legal Observer Guide, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Legal Resources -- National Lawyers Guild NYC Chapter Mass Defense Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Legal Resources -- Occupy Wall Street's Bail Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Legal Resources -- Occupy Wall Street Jail Support Basics (for Manhattan), 2012, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Library Conference Materials -- American Library Association (ALA), 2012 (Box 1, Folder 30, Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 36)
  - Library Conference Materials -- How Class Works: A Conference at SUNY Stony Brook, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Library Conference Materials -- New York Library Association (NYLA), 2012 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Religious Sermons, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series II: Ephemera, Realia, and Protest Materials, 2011-2014; 2011-2012; 3.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, a flat box, an oversized flat box, 4 folders in a shared oversized flat box, and 2 flat file folders
  Materials in this series include ephemera such as stickers, fabric protest signs, buttons, and bookmarks; and posters related to the Occupy Wall Street (OWS) movement and May Day. The protest materials include fliers and informational handouts from OWS events; and affiliated events including May Day, Occupy National Gathering, and Occupy Guitarmy. Some protest materials are not directed at specific events, but rather focus on topics such as Black Lives Matter, student debt forgiveness, universal healthcare, the antiwar movement, and environmentalism. The realia included in this series consists of, but are not limited to: a broken cash box, laptop, books, and Kindle e-reader – all of which were used in the library and retained in the collection, despite their broken state, to document the destruction of the library by the NYPD in November 2011.
  - Ephemera -- Create, Not Hate CodePink.org Fabric Banner, 2011 (Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Ephemera -- Fabric Occupy Wall Street Protest Signs, undated (Box 5)
  - Ephemera -- Labor Sign, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ephemera -- Occupy Wall Street Buttons, undated (Box 5)
  - Ephemera -- Occupy Wall Street Library Bookmarks, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ephemera -- Occupy Wall Street Stickers, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ephemera -- Occupy Wall Street Yellow Police Tape, 2012 (Box 5)
  - Event Flyers, 2011-2012, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Poster -- Journal of Radical Shimming, 99% + 1% = 100%, undated (Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Poster -- May Day, 2012-2013 (Box Shared Tamiment 187, Folder 21)
  - Poster -- Trump, What an Ass, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 1)
  - Poster -- Weatherman Sez, 2011 (Box Shared Tamiment 187, Folder 25)
  - Protest Materials -- Antiwar, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Protest Materials -- Black Lives Matter, 2012, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Protest Materials -- The Body Autonomy and Liberation Ride (Reproductive Rights), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Protest Materials -- Boots on the Ground, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Protest Materials -- Cooper Union, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Protest Materials -- D17, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Protest Materials -- Fracking and Pipelines, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Protest Materials -- Free Palestine, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Protest Materials -- Free Pussy Riot!, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Protest Materials -- Free University and Education Access, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Protest Materials -- Guerilla Librarianship, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Protest Materials -- Healthcare for All, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Protest Materials -- Hurricane Sandy Aid, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Protest Materials -- Immigration, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Protest Materials -- Marijuana Possession, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Protest Materials -- May Day, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy Central Park, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy Guitarmy, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 23, Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 38)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy the Justice Department, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy National Gathering (Philadelphia, PA), 2012 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy Wall Street, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 26, Box 3, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 39)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy Wall Street, ACT UP, and AIDS, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Protest Materials -- Occupy Wall Street Summer Disobedience School, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Protest Materials -- People's Climate March, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Protest Materials -- Prison Reform, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Protest Materials -- Quebec Student Strikes, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Protest Materials -- S17, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Protest Materials -- Socialism, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Protest Materials -- Skin Ride, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Protest Materials -- Student Loan Debt, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Protest Materials -- Unions, 2012-2013 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Protest Materials -- Women in Black, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Protest Materials -- Women Occupying Wall Street, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Protest Materials -- Zero-Fare MTA, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Realia -- Broken Cash Box, undated (Box 5)
  - Realia -- Harmonica, undated (Box 5)
  - Realia -- Kindle, undated (Box 4)
  - Realia -- Laptop, undated (Box 4)
  - Realia -- Light Stick, undated (Box 5)
  - Realia -- Radio Receiver, undated (Box 4)
  - Realia -- Toy NYPD Sign, undated (Box 5)
  - Realia -- Whistle, undated (Box 5)
- Series III: Publications, 1998-2014; 2011-2012; 0.45 Linear Feet in a manuscript box and 8 folders in a shared oversized flat box
  Materials in this series represent publications held by the library, which include publications produced within the Occupy Wall Street (OWS) movements and outside of it. Materials printed by the OWS movement include the Occupied Wall Street Journal, Occupied Washington Post, and Strike Occupy. Materials published outside the OWS movement include a French language newspaper and Arabic language newspaper; radical publications including Fighting for Our Lives: An Anarchist Primer; and Challenge: The Revolutionary Communist Newspapers of Progressive Labor Party; zines published by local artists including Workin' on It! People of Color Experience Occupy Wall Street, Occupied Zuccotti: Social Struggle, and Planned Shrinkage; poetry written by local poet Bob Quinn; and a damaged encyclopedia and worn copy of the Charles Dickens novel Hard Times. An article about librarianship and the OWS Library written by Taylor and Loeb is also included in this series.
  - Article -- "Librarianship Is My Occupation: A History of the People's Library of Occupy Wall Street" by Jaime Taylor and Zachary Loeb, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Books -- Damaged Encyclopedia (Box 6)
  - Books -- Hard Times by Charles Dickens, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Books -- Poetry by Bob Quinn, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Occupy Wall Street Publications -- Occupied Media, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Occupy Wall Street Publications -- The Occupied Wall Street Journal, 2011-2012 (Box Shared Tamiment 187, Folder 19)
  - Occupy Wall Street Publications -- The Occupied Washington Post, 2011 (Box Shared Tamiment 187, Folder 20)
  - Occupy Wall Street Publications -- The Occupied Washington Times, 2011 (Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 37)
  - Occupy Wall Street Publications -- Strike Occupy, 2012 (Box Shared Tamiment 186, Folder 14)
  - Publications -- Challenge: The Revolutionary Communist Newspaper of Progressive Labor Party, 2012 (Box Shared Tamiment 186, Folder 15)
  - Publications -- Fighting for Our Lives: An Anarchist Primer, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publications -- Fireworks: A Bay Area Anarchist News Magazine, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Publications -- Foreign Newspapers, 2012 (Box Shared Tamiment 186, Folder 16)
  - Publications -- The Funny Times (Gift to OWS Library), 2011 (Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 40)
  - Publications -- Harbinger, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 41)
  - Zines -- The 99% Guide to the Current Clusterfuck, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Zines -- The Debt Resistors' Operational Manual, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Zines -- Economics for the 99%, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Zines -- Every Reason #7, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Zines -- Gag Me With A..., 2011 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Zines -- If You See Something, Say Something by Catherine Wald, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Zines -- May 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Zines -- May Day 1971, or How to Lose Street Battles and Alienate People, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Zines -- Nonviolence and Its Violent Consequences by William Meyers, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Zines -- Occupied Zuccotti: Social Struggle and Planned Shrinkage, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Zines -- Peggy Kornegger Anarchism: The Feminist Connection, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Zines -- A Preliminary Glance at the Occupy Wall Street Review by Peter Lamborn Wilson, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Zines -- Rousseau's Theory of the State by Michael Balkunin, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Zines -- Self Poor Trait, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Zines -- Whatever Used to Grow Here by Lauren Belski, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Zines -- Workin' On It! People of Color Experience Occupy Wall Street, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Zines -- Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.), 2012 (Box 3, Folder 34)